Inventory of the Eunice Burton Armstrong papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Eunice Burton Armstrong papers
1932-1941
2011C28
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 2 card file boxes, 1 oversize folder (5.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, notes, bulletins, newsletters, clippings, other printed matter, mailing lists, and address cards relating to the efforts of the America First Committee to ensure American neutrality during World War II. Includes issuances of, and correspondence with, other peace organizations.
Armstrong, Eunice Burton, 1887-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Eunice Burton Armstrong was born in 1887 in Waterford, New York. She received a BA in English from Mt. Holyoke College, Massachusetts in 1908 and an MA in economics, social legislation and psychology from Columbia University in 1912. Armstrong finished her post-graduate education at the New York School of Social Work and later became a psychologist. Her career included teaching, writing, and speaking on womens' suffrage, public health, and psychology. Armstrong married Donald Budd Armstrong, a physician, in 1913. They raised four sons, Donald Budd, Jr., Stewart, Lincoln, and Burton.
Armstrong was assistant editor of the Archives of Psychoanalysis and performed research for the Encyclopedia of Social Forces. In addition to her professional writing, Armstrong became involved with writing editorials for small town newspapers. She also wrote publicity for the amendment to the Selective Service Act prohibiting use of drafted men outside the United States.
Armstrong’s work experience also included performing taxation and housing studies, as well as serving as a New York State Factory Inspector (1910-1913). As field director of the New York City Department of Welfare, Armstrong was in charge of 140 inspectors who were investigating orphan asylums. She later was a consultant psychologist for school and private patients for 15 years.
Armstrong became Educational Director of the America First Committee’s New York Chapter in 1941. The America First Committee was a non-interventionist, political pressure group that existed from 1940 to 1941, urging the United States government not to enter World War II. Armstrong's other affiliations included the Massachusetts Suffrage Committee, the Westchester Planned Parenthood League, and the District Nursing Association (Ossining, New York).
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, notes, bulletins, newsletters, clippings, other printed matter, mailing lists, and address cards relating to the efforts of the America First Committee to ensure American neutrality during World War II and other anti-war campaigns.
The collection contains newsletters and printed matter published by the America First Committee, as well as materials from other peace and womens' organizations, including: the National Council for the Prevention of War (NCPW), the People's Lobby, Women Investors in America, Women Patriots of the Republic, Women United to Preserve America, Silver Star Mothers, and We, the Mothers, Mobilize for America.
Arrangement Statement
Files are grouped according to Armstrong's original file system. Un-filed materials were placed in existing groupings and filed chronologically, then alphabetically. For ease of use, the bulk of the mailing labels have been separated and placed in boxes 8 and 9.
Related Collections
America First Committee records, Hoover Institution Archives.
Fight for Freedom Committee records, Hoover Institution Archives.
Ruth Sarles typescript: A history of America First, Hoover Institution Archives.
America First Committee. New York Chapter, Inc.; America First Committee.; United States--Neutrality.; United States--Non-interventionalism.; Women--Political activity--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Peace.; World War, 1939-1945--Protest movements.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- America First Committee File, 1936-1941
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes minutes, correspondence, clippings, memoranda, radio bulletins, and printed matter.
  The collection also contains clean and annotated copies of the America First Committee publication entitled Bulletin, which can be found in box 4.
  - Research files, 1936 February-1941 August (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Contains printed matter on Charles Lindberg and the "Youth for America First" report.
  - Memoranda and organizational records, 1940 April-1941 October (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Correspondence and clippings, 1941 January-1941 December
    Includes fever charts and correspondence lists noting those who opposed or supported initiatives, as well as drafts, samples of chain letters, congressional correspondence from Senators Joseph Ball, W. Warren Barbour and James T. Davis, and appeal letters to House members.
    - Congressional correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Campaigns and events, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Recruitment letters, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Peace Organizations File, circa 1937-1941
  Correspondence, newsletters, official pamphlets, and other printed matter regarding peace rallies and other campaigns led by organizations such as the National Council for the Prevention of War (NCPW) and the People's Lobby.
  - Materials, circa 1937-1941 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - National Council for the Prevention of War records, 1940 October-1941 November (Box-folder 1: 7)
- America First Women's Division File, 1941
  Organizational records, including documentation of the May 1941 Washington, DC rally.
  - Campaigns and correspondence, 1941 March-1941 October (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Finance committee records, 1941 May-1941 December (Box-folder 2: 2)
- Womens' Organizations Records, 1939-1941
  Clippings, correspondence and printed matter from various womens' peace organizations.
  - Women Investors in America and others, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - We, the Mothers, Mobilize for America and others, 1940 September-1941 December (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Westchester League of Women Voters and Women United, 1941 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Women United, 1941
    Includes printed matter, appeal letters, correspondence, telegrams, press releases, agenda, list of womens' national organizations, membership blanks, notes, clippings, and correspondence.
    - Washington, DC rally and Save Our Sons (SOS) campaign files, 1941 January-1941 August (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Correspondence and mailing lists, 1941 March-April (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Administrative records, 1941 March-October (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Subject File, 1932-1941
  Includes congressional voting records, clippings, correspondence, and other materials on the topics of conscription (Selective Service), Lend Lease Bill (H.R. 1776), Neutrality Acts of 1937 to 1939, non-internventionalism, and anti-Semitism. Armstrong's original order was maintained.
  - Anti-Semitic and pro-Jewish materials, 1932 August-1941 October (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Contains clippings, correspondence, and printed matter on or about anti-Semitism, with some annotations. Also includes the monograph, "The Jew Who Helped Save America," by Charles Spencer Hart and a brochure from the National Conference of Christians and Jews.
  - Conscription, 1940 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    Includes petitions, volunteer sign-up sheets, letter samples, and mailing lists.
  - Lend Lease Bill, 1940-1941
    - Files, 1941 January-April (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Recruitment and "Wear Our Emblem" campaign, 1941 February-April (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Correspondence and printed matter, 1941 April-August (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Printed matter, circa 1940 November-1941 February (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Neutrality Act, 1940-1941
    - Correspondence and printed matter, 1940 April-1941 November (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Repeal correspondence and printed matter, 1941 October-November (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Non-intervention files, 1941 October (Box-folder 3: 9)
- Printed Matter, 1940-1941
  - America First Committee Bulletin, 1941 February-December (Box 4)
    Consists of issues 45 to 700 of Bulletin, a mass-mailed publication by the America First Committee highlighting the Committee's activities. The bulletins excerpt radio speeches, articles, quotations from political figures, and inter-chapter communications. Some topics include anti-war, conscription, the Lend Lease Bill, and the Neutrality Act. Remarks from and about Senator Hamilton Fish and Charles Lindberg are also included.
    Bulletin is arranged by issue number where available and chronologically. Annotated bulletins follow the original order of the creator.
    - 45 to 199, 1941 February-April (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 200s, 1941 April-May (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 300s, 1941 June-July (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 400s, 1941 July (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - 500s, 1941 August-October (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - 601 to 700, 1941 October-December (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Annotated copies, 1941 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Other America First Committee publications, 1940-1941
    - Pamphlets and ephemera, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - National headquarters and other regional chapters, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Washington Newsletter, 1941 February-June (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Chapter Chatter newsletter, 1941 June-August (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - America First Committee sash and ephemeral materials, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Clippings, 1940-1941
    Includes some correspondence.
    - America First Committee news, polls and annotated clippings, 1941 April-October (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - Anti-war rallies, 1941 May-November (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Editorial cartoons on Lend-Lease bill, Charles Lindberg, and anti-war topics, 1940 July-1941 October (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Pamphlets and other publications such as Affairs and The Commonwealth, circa 1940-1941 (Box-folder 5: 9)
- Mailings, circa 1941
  Mailing labels and mailing lists are organized into geographic areas and are also grouped by organization. Files contain some indexes, while other files are a compilation of petitions with addresses. Most labels are local New York City and New York State addresses.
  Boxes 8 and 9 contain labels that cover regional and national geographic areas. Labels are gummed, perforated and typewritten with names and addresses (about 33 people per page).
  - New York, Anglican clergy and Catholic churches, circa 1941 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Marked "Keep Separate,", 1940-1941 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    Contains correspondence, clippings, petitions, and lists from Massachusetts, as well as addresses in New York State.
  - Marked "Scarsdale,", circa 1941 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    Contains Peekskill and Ossining, New York addresses.
  - Card files, circa 1941 (Boxes 6-7)
    Index cards include handwritten addresses and notes. Most are separated by geographic areas, while some are grouped according to batches, in the original order of the creator.
  - Mailing labels, circa 1941 (Boxes 8-9)
    Typewritten address labels of various groups, including Mayflower Descendents, Daughters of American Colonists, Daughters of the American Revolution, Gold Star Mothers, League of Women Voters, and the Womens' National Republican Club. Volume one (box 8) includes lists of Republican groups, with a partial index of mailing lists, and volume two (box 9) includes general New York lists.
- Oversize Material, 1940-1941
  - America First Bulletin, 1941 May-December (Oversize-box 10: 1-2)
    Published by the America First Committee's New York Chapter, Inc. Includes clean and annotated copies covering topics such as the Neutrality Act repeal and other campaigns.
  - Anti-war clippings, 1941 April-December (Oversize-box 10: 3)
    From publications such as The Chicago Daily Tribune, Citizen Register (Ossining, New York), PM Magazine, the New York Post, and the New York Herald.
  - Newspapers covering anti-war topics, 1940 July-1941 December (Oversize-box 10: 4-5)
    Includes America First Committee's The Herald (from the San Francisco-Northern California chapter), as well as The Catholic Worker, American Mothers National Weekly, The American Guardian, The People Sentinel, and The Progressive (founded in 1909 by Senator Robert La Follette).
  - Women United mock-ups of anti-war rally posters, 1941 April-May (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - America First Committee poster, undated (Map case)